<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Freedom Matters</title><link href="https://freedommatters.top/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://freedommatters.top/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://freedommatters.top/</id><updated>2024-11-13T14:54:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Chinese Society - A Network of Personal Relationships</title><link href="https://freedommatters.top/chinese-society-a-network-of-personal-relationships.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-11-13T14:54:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Anonymous</name></author><id>tag:https://freedommatters.top,2024-11-13:chinese-society-a-network-of-personal-relationships.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Chinese society, people are typically born within a network of personal relationships. Rather than adhering to formal rules, which are seen as applying to outsiders, Chinese people prefer to operate through unwritten understandings among their social connections.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Western societies emphasize universal and equitable rules as the bedrock of social order. There's no need to navigate complex social relationships – simply following the established rules suffices, regardless of who you're dealing with.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China has demonstrated its capacity to adapt to modern rule-based systems, as evidenced by its decades of economic development in alignment with international norms.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, things have shifted recently due to growing overconfidence among many Chinese. It is particularly evident in the current Chinese government under Xi's leadership, which has developed an inflated sense of China's importance, believing the world cannot function without them. They've started to dismiss systems and values they once respected.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What fuels this overconfidence? It stems largely from China's role as the world's manufacturing hub. In areas where they've achieved technological competence through adaptation and refinement, they believe they can challenge existing international norms. They demand a seat at the table in shaping future international rules and insist on being treated with deference. Essentially, they're trying to apply the principles of relationship-based governance to international relations. They view their disregard for established rules, and even their creation of new ones, as a privilege earned through their economic and industrial might.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, international rules aren't created in a vacuum – they're the product of long-term interaction between nations, deeply rooted in historical, cultural, and political realities. While the international community can be accommodating on minor issues during peaceful times, any attempt to fundamentally challenge or upend the existing world order inevitably faces pushback. This fundamental disconnect explains the growing tension and confrontation between China and the Western world.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;中国人在绝大多数情况下，生于熟人社会，死于熟人社会。他们倾向于在熟人关系中建立默契，而不太愿意尊重所谓的规则，因为规则是对外人的，不是对熟人的。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;而西方人则更注重规则的普遍性和公平性，认为规则是维系社会秩序的基础。无论有没有熟人，按照规则办事即可，不必折腾应酬搞熟人社会的那一套。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;其实中国也有能力融入现代规则。中国过去的几十年在经济上的发展，就是遵循了通行的国际规则。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;而今发生了变化是因为有很多中国人开始自大了，他们认为原先非常重视看重，高看的一些东西，没有什么特殊的。尤其是当下的中国政府，在习的带领下，产生了一种幻觉，认为这个世界离开中国就得停摆，必须要正视中国。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这种过分的自信是基于什么呢？基于中国目前能够给整个世界提供的工业品。他们认为在所有他们可以二次创新的领域中，他们具备挑战现行国际规则的能力。他们要求在制定未来的国际规则的过程中，一定要有他们参与，并且他们需要得到尊重。他们试图将熟人社会中的经验套用到国际关系中。他们把无视规则，甚至可以随意创造规则当作一种任性，而且是非常有底气，基于实力的任性。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;国际规则是各国在长期互动中逐步形成的共识，其背后蕴含着深厚的历史、文化和政治因素。在和平环境中，在不触及到原则性问题的时候，国际社会往往会表现出包容态度。而一旦试图挑战甚至颠覆现有的国际秩序，必然会遭到国际社会的抵制。这也是目前中国和整个西方社会出现分歧，走入对抗的根本原因。&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--

&lt;iframe class="youtube-video" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G2rUXrcs-sE?si=GmRh4CcK8zl4f-Ra" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

--&gt;</summary><category term="relationships"></category><category term="rules"></category></entry><entry><title>The Unknown Protester</title><link href="https://freedommatters.top/the-unknown-protester.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-06-04T16:24:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Anonymous</name></author><id>tag:https://freedommatters.top,2024-06-04:the-unknown-protester.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What would you do when facing an invincible and powerful opponent?&lt;br&gt;
在面对自己不可战胜的强大对手时，你会怎么做？&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an old Chinese saying, "Those who follow me will prosper, while those who oppose me will perish." It's unwise to defy the powerful. Most of us become submissive after experiencing injustice and having nowhere to resort to. Therefore, when facing the powerful or experiencing injustice in our later life, we often choose to downplay and avoid confrontations rather than bravely defending our rights, We can only console ourselves with the thought "settle things amicably" and "the less trouble, the better".&lt;br&gt;
中国自古就有“顺我者昌，逆我者亡”的说法，强权不可忤逆。大多数人都会在经历大大小小的“社会毒打”后变得顺从。所以面对强权时，遭遇不公时我们往往不会选择“勇敢维权”，而是选择淡化回避，“息事宁人”、并且自我安慰“多一事不如少一事”。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, when seeing others experiencing injustice, most people choose to be bystanders. Some of them are indifferent and numb to the situation, some gloat, some want to step forward and help but lack the means to do so.&lt;br&gt;
与此相对，当他人遭遇不公时大多数人则会选择冷眼旁观，有的人见怪不怪、麻木以对，有的人幸灾乐祸看笑话，有的人想上前帮忙却心有余而力不足。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another type of people tie themselves to the chariot of the powerful, using themselves as tools, riding on the coattails of the powerful. They gain recognition and profit from the powerful by helping to suppress their own kind more aggressively than the powerful.&lt;br&gt;
另一类人会把自己绑在强权的战车上，把自己当做工具，虎假虎威，为虎作伥，通过帮助更激进地打压同类而获得强权的认可获利。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is also a type of group who uphold justice and maintain their beliefs, and actively and bravely expresse their resistance against injustice, even if it's like "a mantis trying to stop a chariot."&lt;br&gt;
当然，还有一类人，他们坚持公义，坚定信念，积极勇敢表达对不公的反抗，即便是螳臂当车。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we need to become the last type, especially living in an unjust social framework. Because there's no guarantee that injustice won't happen to us.&lt;br&gt;
也许，我们更需要成为最后一类人，尤其是在一个框架不公的环境中。因为难保不公的事不会发生在我们身上。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The confession prose "First they came"&lt;br&gt;
引用一首忏悔诗：&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;First they came for the socialists
and I did not speak out
Because I was not a socialist

Then they came for the trade unionists
and I did not speak out&amp;lt;
Because I was not a trade unionist

Then they came for the Jews
and I did not speak out
Because I was not a Jew

Then they came for me
and there was no one left to speak for me
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;起初他们朝民主人士下手
我沉默，因为我不是民运份子

当他们迫害宗教信仰人士时
我沉默，我也不是教徒

当他们镇压维权人士的时候
我沉默，因为我也不是维权人士

最后当他们来抓我时
我放眼四周，身边有的也只是沉默的看客。
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show our respect to those who actively and bravely resist, and pay tribute to those who are like a mantis trying to stop a chariot.&lt;br&gt;
致敬那些积极勇敢反抗的人们，致敬那些螳臂当车的人们。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="youtube-video" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G2rUXrcs-sE?si=GmRh4CcK8zl4f-Ra" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</summary><category term="8964"></category><category term="Tank Man"></category></entry><entry><title>Jimmy Lai on 60 Minutes in 2019</title><link href="https://freedommatters.top/jimmy-lai-on-60-minutes.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-06-03T09:12:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Anonymous</name></author><id>tag:https://freedommatters.top,2024-06-03:jimmy-lai-on-60-minutes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At 71, Jimmy Lai has lived the Hong Kong dream. Born in mainland China, he fled the communists when he was 12 years old. He went from rags to riches, from a worker in a textile factory to a billionaire with a chain of fashion stores. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1989, when Chinese tanks massacred students in Beijing's Tiananmen Square, he got involved in politics, starting a media company in Hong Kong that isn't afraid to criticize the Chinese government.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jimmy Lai: I like to participate in delivering information. Because I think information is freedom. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He told us Hong Kongers are demanding real democracy and are fighting to hold on to their basic human rights. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jimmy Lai: The intention of the Chinese government taking away our freedom is so obvious that we know, if we don't fight, we will lose everything. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holly Williams: What do you mean lose everything?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jimmy Lai: When you lose the freedom, you lose everything. What do you have?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holly Williams: I mean, you have a wonderful city, prosperity.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jimmy Lai: That's what Chinese think. They think that we just have a body, we don't have a soul. "You guys just make money, have a good life. Don't think about politics. Don't think about freedom. Don't think about human right. Don't think about rule of law. Just eat. Enjoy life."&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holly Williams: Why is that not enough?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jimmy Lai: Because we are human being. We have soul. We are not a dog.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="youtube-video" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yVwPmEBcVYg?si=Y-apbF2zq-BIP96a" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</summary><category term="Jimmy Lai"></category><category term="Freedom"></category><category term="Freedom Matters"></category><category term="8964"></category></entry><entry><title>Tripping Alone</title><link href="https://freedommatters.top/tripping-alone.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-05-06T12:35:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Anonymous</name></author><id>tag:https://freedommatters.top,2024-05-06:tripping-alone.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I do not know what the destination would be, but at least I am on the way.&lt;br&gt;
我不知道未來怎樣，但至少我已在路上。&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lyrics from White Dove as below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facing ahead, there's no direction,&lt;br&gt;
前方啊 沒有方向&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my body, there's no clothing.&lt;br&gt;
身上啊 沒有了衣裳&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blood is seeping from my wings,&lt;br&gt;
鮮血啊 滲出了翅膀&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tear is wetting my chest.&lt;br&gt;
我的眼淚 濕透了胸膛&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flying, enduring the pain,&lt;br&gt;
飛翔著 強忍著傷&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I escaped from the hunter's gun.&lt;br&gt;
逃離了 獵人的槍&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear mother, beloved friends,&lt;br&gt;
親愛的母親 摯愛的朋友&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will stay perseverant,&lt;br&gt;
我會堅定 好好的活&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with everlasting wounds,&lt;br&gt;
縱然帶著永遠的傷口&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least I still possess freedom.&lt;br&gt;
至少我還擁有自由&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="player" class="aplayer"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
var ap = new APlayer({
    element: document.getElementById('player'),
    narrow: false,
    autoplay: true,
    showlrc: false,
    mutex: true,
    theme: '#615754',
    mode: 'circulation',
    preload: 'auto',
    music: {title: 'White Dove',author: 'Wu Bai',
                url: 'https://i.freedommatters.top/tripping-alone/white-dove.mp3',
                pic: 'http://p1.music.126.net/RapqPMQnRyfW2J7w8k0u8A==/109951165611292291.jpg',}
    });
&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="trip alone"></category></entry></feed>